So, I reckon you want to know about the
role Big Daddy government played in the
economy during the Gilded Age. Well,
butter my backside and call me a biscuit
because that's exactly what this video
is about. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, now I've mentioned this already in
several previous videos, but let me
remind you that in general Big Daddy
government took a laissez-faire approach
to economics during the Gilded Age. And
that's a French phrase that literally
means leave alone or let alone, which is
to say the federal government tended to
keep its hands off the national economy
during the Gilded Age. And there were
several key reasons that the government
took that posture, but for now you just
need to know that the debate about the
role of the federal government in the
economy is one that stretches back to
the founding of our country. Like
remember that that was a main beef
between Alexander Hamilton and Thomas
Jefferson with respect to the creation
of a national bank. And it reared its
head again when debates over Henry
Clay's American system erupted in
Congress, and they argued fiercely about
whether the government ought to sponsor
infrastructure improvements like roads
and canals. And I could go on, but the
point is controversies over the role of
government in the economy is not a new
thing during this period. But there is a
big difference between those examples I
just mentioned and the economics during
this period. You see, the creation of
the national bank and the implementation
of the American system policies
demonstrate Big Daddy government getting
real hands-on with economic policy. But
during the Gilded Age those hands came
right off and laissez-faire the crap out
of the economy. And if you want to know
the three ideological reasons behind
that change, then I'm about to explain
it up real nice for you. But first, let
me just say that a laissez-faire
hands-off approach to studying for APUSH
is not going to work. If you need help
getting an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May, then you might want to
check out my APUSH highly review guide
which has everything you need to study
as fast as possible. link is down in the
description. Anyway, the first idea that
contributed to laissez-faire economic
policies was the growing acceptance in
America that hard work necessarily
resulted in economic prosperity. For
example, I mentioned in a previous video
the exceedingly popular novels of
Horatio Alger, which contributed to this
idea since his characters often rose
from rags to riches on account of their
own talents and hard work. Additionally,
Christian leaders like Baptist pastor
Russell Conwell preached exceedingly
popular sermons in which he equated
building wealth honestly with the
preaching of the gospel. And of course,
ideas like Conwell's were in direct
contradiction to the social gospel
movement that was going on at the same
time. You see, to Conwell, if a person
was poor, that was a clear sign that God
was withholding wealth from them on
account of their sins. And that was an
idea deeply connected to social
Darwinism and the gospel of wealth since
by Conwell's reckoning, wealth was a
sign that a person was in fact virtuous
and poverty was a sign of vice, all of
which had a way of justifying poverty in
a capitalist economy. But to the
adherents of the social gospel, poverty
was most often the result
inequalities that the poor were often
powerless to overcome. But the hard work
always equals prosperity belief was held
by most policy makers in the halls of
power and that very much contributed to
the laissez-faire approach to economic
policy. Therefore, in light of all of
that, social and economic mobility was
more and more understood by the elites
to be a meritocracy. In other words, the
best and most resourceful people and
businesses would always rise to the top
and that would be the reward for hard
work. And that means with such a
conviction guiding American thought,
wealthy industrialists opposed
government intervention in business
affairs because it would hinder their
merit-based success. Okay, then the
second set of ideas that contributed to
a laissez-faire approach to economics
were the principles of free market
economics first articulated by Adam
Smith in 1776. So, in his book The
Wealth of Nations, Smith argued that
nations gain wealth to the degree that
they allow the invisible hand of the
market, guided by the laws of supply and
demand, to organize their economic
relationships. In other words, Smith's
main formula for economic flourishing
was to restrain all outside and
artificial influences on the market,
most notably the government. Now, as far
as ideas go, that one's real nice and
all, but there was a big honking problem
with applying Smith's ideas to the
actual economic reality of Gilded Age
America. You see, while Gilded Age
politicians and tycoons were spouting
off about Adam Smith and the invisible
hand, apparently they forgot that the
economic environment that they had
created was nothing like what Adam Smith
envisioned. For example, one vital
ingredient for a prosperous economy in
Smith's view is competition, but these
business leaders had so consolidated
power in their respective industries
that competition had vanished like a
fart in the wind. And so, even when a
nation's economy took a nosedive and
working people were suffering real bad,
Smith's prescription was simply to let
the market correct itself over time
without government intervention. And
that was great for the wealthy people
since they had plenty of boom-boom to
alleviate their suffering. And there's
probably no better example of the
influence of this kind of thought than
President Grover Cleveland's veto of the
Texas Seed Bill in 1887. In that year,
Texan farmers were suffering terribly as
a result of a long drought. And with no
grass to graze, something like 85% of
their cattle had died and the farmers on
the brink starvation had eaten much of
their seed corn, which meant they had
nothing to plant for the next year. And
so, in response, Congress passed the
Texas Seed Bill, which appropriated
money for these farmers to buy corn seed
for that year's planting. Wow, that's
really great. Like Americans are
starving and a government of the people,
by the people, and for the people is
reaching out to alleviate that misery.
But, here comes old laissez-faire
President Cleveland to take a dump on
such relief. Yeah, Cleveland actually
vetoed the Texas Seed Bill because, and
I quote, "Though the people support the
government, the government should not
support the people." forget that it was
also President Cleveland who used the
military to break the Pullman strike,
which we talked about in a previous
video. So, yeah, he was a fun guy.
Anyway, thirdly, laissez-faire policies
were supported by the growing adherence
to the principles of social Darwinism.
And I flapped my mouth hole about this
in detail in a previous video, so I'll
keep it short. Basically, the idea was
that if the government propped up weaker
Americans and weaker businesses, then it
would ultimately hurt the long-term
prosperity and flourishing of the
American economic system. So, if you put
all those three big ideas in a pot,
then, baby, you've got a stew going. And
that stew tastes like a minimal
government intervention in the economy,
which allowed industrialists to
consolidate metric butt-loads of power
and wealth. However, it's very important
to remember that while industrialists
and business leaders argued fiercely
against government intervention when it
hindered their business practices, they
were perfectly happy to accept help from
Big Daddy Government when it benefited
them. For example, big businesses often
pushed Congress for protective tariffs
that encouraged Americans to buy
domestic products instead of foreign
goods. And don't forget that it was the
federal government that granted massive
tracts of land to railroad companies,
which facilitated the construction of
several transcontinental railroads. And
like I just mentioned, business leaders
also called upon federal troops to break
labor strikes as they did in the Pullman
strike in 1894. And I could go on, but
you get the point. Okay, now there's one
other big economic development that
you'll need to know for this topic. So,
the rapid industrialization of the
United States sparked fervent desires
among foreign policy makers to gain
control of foreign markets and natural
resources outside the United States. And
why was that, says you? Well, says I,
because the American manufacturing
sector had become so wildly productive,
the fear was that current foreign
markets, mostly in Europe and Canada, be
capable of buying all those excess goods
being made. And so, that meant that
Americans needed to look elsewhere both
for new markets and natural resources.
And there were three main areas in which
they did so. First, policy makers looked
to gain control of territories in the
Pacific Rim, most notably Hawaii. And if
you recall from the video on 6.6, big
American sugar companies like Castle and
Cook rapidly gained control over the
islands and the indigenous people who
lived there, a process that was
kickstarted by American missionaries on
the islands. And once the Hawaiian
economy became a vital ingredient in the
American economy, white Americans led a
coup to topple the indigenous
government, and in 1898, Congress
approved the annexation of Hawaii. Okay,
second, policy makers wanted to gain
influence in Asia, most notably China.
So, seeing how missionary activity
facilitated the annexation of Hawaii,
Congress pressured China to sign the
Burlingame Treaty in 1868. Essentially,
it allowed American missionaries free
access to evangelize in China while also
securing a much more open and profitable
trade relationship between the two
countries by granting the United States
what's known as a most favored nation
status. Additionally, this treaty opened
the US to much more Chinese immigration
to America, which made business leaders
real happy since they now had a flood of
cheap labor and a metric buttload of new
Chinese markets for their goods. And to
be clear, this is about 15 years before
the Chinese Exclusion Act was passed, so
all those Chinese immigrants would at
least have that to look forward to. And
finally, policy makers looked to gain
influence in Alaska. To that end, in
1867, the Secretary of State William
Seward entered negotiations with the
Russian government to purchase the
Alaskan territory for $7.2 million. And
a lot of powerful Americans thought
Seward was crazy because Alaska just
like nothing but a barren frozen
wasteland. But in Seward's mind, Alaska
would serve as a strong American
launching pad to enter Asian markets.
However, in 1896, gold was discovered
under its frigid soil and thus began the
rapid American population of Alaska
during the Klondike Gold Rush. And
that's when Seward looked around and was
like, "How y'all like me now?" Anyway,
as a result, Alaska became both an entry
to new markets in Asia while also
granting the US access to enormous
amounts of natural resources like gold
and then later oil. Okay, click here to
keep watching my other Unit 6 videos or
you can click here to grab my A Push
Heimler Review Guide which has
everything you need to get an A in your
class and a five on your exam in May.
I'm glad you came around and I'll catch
you on the flip flop. I'm Heimler out.